<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An abstract of the argument in Mr. Turner's papers concerning the marriage of an uncle with the daughter of his half-brother by the father's side</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3298A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16211</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13355056</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13355056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 479:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An abstract of the argument in Mr. Turner's papers concerning the marriage of an uncle with the daughter of his half-brother by the father's side</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Incest --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99229:1"/>
            <p>AN ABSTRACT OF THE ARGUMENT IN Mr. <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER</hi>'s PAPERS Concerning the MARRIAGE OF AN UNCLE With the DAUGHTER OF HIS HALF-BROTHER BY THE Father's-ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb facs="tcp:99229:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99229:2"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT OF THE ARGUMENT IN Mr. <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER</hi>'s PAPERS Concerning <hi>The Marriage of an</hi> Uncle <hi>with the</hi> Daughter <hi>of his</hi> Half-Brother <hi>by the</hi> Fathers <hi>ſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIRST, The aforeſaid Marriage is not expreſly forbidden in any Act of Parliament, wherein the Degrees prohibited are ſet down.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is not expreſsly mention'd in the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, which the Law of <hi>England</hi> follows as its Pattern.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Law of <hi>England,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99229:3"/> in its Penal Sanctions, hath no regard to Parity of Reaſon; and the Caſe is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame in Priviledges or Exemptions: This appears by ſeveral Proofs alledged to this purpoſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 25, 26, 27. of the Firſt Diſcourſe. And this is likewiſe prov'd more largely by three other Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mention'd afterwards, <hi>pag.</hi> 68, 69, 70. The Firſt is of a Priviledge allow'd by Act of Parliament to a <hi>Knights</hi> eldeſt Son, which ſhall not extend to the eldeſt Son of a <hi>Baronet.</hi> The Second is a Matrimonial Cuſtom, concerning the Marriage of two Brothers to two Siſters, or of Brother and Siſter to Siſter and Brother; or of the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-law to the Mother-in-laws Daughter, or Father-in-laws Daughter, which are not ſo much as pretended to be diſallow'd by our Law, notwithſtanding they are all of them ſo great and manifeſt violations of the great and fundamental Reaſon; if all theſe Prohibitions, which was to ſpread Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and propagate Good-will and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt Men, by not reſtraining the Matrimonial Affinities within too narrow a a compaſs. The Third is taken from the expreſs words of the Statute, 25 <hi>H. 8. c.</hi> 22. wherein the particular prohibited Degrees which are there enumerated and ſet down are uſher'd in with a, <hi>that is to ſay;</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99229:3"/> there is reference made to the ſaid Degrees by the words <hi>Afore rehearſed,</hi> and <hi>above expreſſed;</hi> by which it is manifeſt, that this Act ſticks cloſely to its own Letter, without admitting Parities or probable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, it being abſurd to ſuppoſe the words <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> to refer to thoſe particulars, of which no mention after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards is made; or that the words <hi>afore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed,</hi> or <hi>above expreſſed,</hi> can refer to ſuch <hi>pretended</hi> Inſtances of Prohibition as are <hi>no where</hi> rehearſed or expreſſed; for certainly it is one thing to <hi>rehearſe</hi> or to <hi>expreſs,</hi> and another to <hi>intimate,</hi> to <hi>infer,</hi> to <hi>argue</hi> by Parities, Conſequences, or Deductions, how natural, eaſie, and genuine ſoever they be: And this is ſtill farther made out againſt the exception of my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Vaughan, pag.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16. of the <hi>Addenda &amp; Mutanda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Learned Men are divided in their Opinions concerning the Nature of theſe Laws, whether they be Natural or meerly poſitive: Among the latter ſort are <hi>Paulus Burgenſis, Cajetanus, C. à Lapide, Sanchez,</hi> and the Authors by him cited, <hi>Tirinus, Lorinus, Menochius,</hi> and <hi>Magalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> And among the Reform'd, three great Authorities, <hi>Druſius, Epiſcopius,</hi> and our Learned Biſhop <hi>Taylor;</hi> and they that with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99229:4"/> theſe Gentlemen are of this Opinion, that the obligation of theſe Laws is poſitive and no more, they have no pretence for a diſſolution of this Marriage; becauſe, in Laws meerly poſitive, there is no ſuch thing as Parity to be admitted, ſuch Laws being all of them a manifeſt reſtraint upon the Natural Liberties of Mankind, and therefore ought not to be ſtrain'd by Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Interpretations, whether true or falſe, beyond the Letter of them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though we ſhould allow the prohibitions of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> to proceed all of them upon the Meaſures of Nature, yet though the Laws are Natural, the Sanction of them is poſitive, and no more; for God might have aſſigned other puniſhments if he had pleas'd, as Servitude, hard Labor, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, Fine, Confiſcation, Impriſonment, the loſs of any Limb, or Member, or any other Puniſhment ſhort of life it ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of diſparagement to his Juſtice, or any violation of the Laws of Nature, wherefore in ſo great variety of poſſible infliction, what puniſhment can we aſſign as an Act of Obedience to the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical</hi> Law, when that Law it ſelf hath not aſſign'd any?</p>
            <p>Adultery by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Death in both parties, but by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99229:4"/> ours it is not ſo, which is a plain Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whatever may be ſaid of unlawful Marriages, or unlawful Luſts, in which we are govern'd by the <hi>Levitical</hi> Meaſures; yet, as to the puniſhments conſequent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, we have Meaſures of our own; and therefore where no Puniſhment is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly determined by our Law, or at leaſt expreſly left to the Diſcretion of the Judge, or Court, or of any other Perſon or Perſons to whom the Cognizance of the Matter ſhall appertain; in this Caſe no Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can lawfully be inflicted: How then can we with Juſtice proceed to a Divorce in caſe of ſuch a Marriage as to which the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law is ſilent as well as ours?</p>
            <p>So likewiſe in the Caſe of <hi>Buggery</hi> or <hi>Beſtiality,</hi> it was Death without Mercy by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and ſo it is by ours made Felony without benefit of Clergy; but this was not till the 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. and if by that or ſome other Statute, proviſion had not been made, we muſt either ſay, that that Act of Parliament was altogether fruitleſs, or elſe, that it would not have been Capital to this Moment. Wherefore there being no Puniſhment expreſly aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or expreſly left to the Judgment and Diſcretion of any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>other</hi> Judge by our Law, though it had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99229:5"/> prohibited, and more than that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly puniſhable by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for a Man to Marry his Niece; yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it could not have been ſo by ours.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practice and uſage of our Laws are not prohibited to Marry with each other, notwithſtanding the Diſpenſation granted to the Daughters of <hi>Zelophehad,</hi> which Diſpenſation ſhews it undeniably to have been prohibited in all ordinary Caſes, and, as it was, it concerned only the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State, and the preſervation of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Platform of Inheritances among that People, I ſay, if they are notwithſtanding allow'd to Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marry, meerly for this Reaſon, becauſe they are not expreſly mention'd in that Act of Parliament, wherein the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Degrees are ſpecified and ſet down, how ſhall not then the ſame priviledge be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the ſame, and for a greater Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> and the <hi>Niece,</hi> who are not only not expreſly mentioned as Perſons prohibited and diſallowed by our Law, but are not ſo much as mentioned in the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> it ſelf, where <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> are undeniably forbidden?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, In the <hi>Eighteenth</hi> of thoſe Canons which are called <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99229:5"/> are without queſtion of great Antiquity and Authority in the Church, A Man that Marries his Brothers Daughter is not by virtue of the ſaid Canon divorc'd from his ſaid Marriage, or excluded from the Communion of the Church, or debarr'd any other Priviledge, or Immunity of a Chriſtian Man, or of a Member of the Body Politick, or Eccleſiaſtick whatſoever; only for Examples ſake, he is not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to enter into Holy Orders; which though it ſhew ſufficiently, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of theſe Canons were againſt all Marriages in this Degree, and therefore the Clergy were prohibited for an Example to others; yet it is plain, that at the ſame time they did not look upon it as a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage prohibited or deteſted by the Law of God, and ſuch as Chriſtianity, which hath a more tender regard to the propagation of Friendſhip and Good-will, than the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> had, lays an abſolute and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable obligation upon us to avoid: And this being, as it is, ſuch a plain teſtimony of the Opinion of the Ancient Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Marriages of this Nature, carries great Weight and Authority along with it, for the deciding this particular Caſe in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the parties that are concerned in it.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99229:6"/>
            <p>Eighthly, Though this Marriage ſhould be granted to be antecedently prohibited and unlawful; yet it doth not preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that being actually Solemniz'd and Conſummated by fruition, it ſhall be made null and void.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> in his Firſt Paper hath given ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral<note place="margin">
                  <hi>From. p. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o 18. Pag.</hi> 42, 43, 44, ib. &amp; in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. <hi>pag.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> inſtances of unlawful Acts, which yet notwithſtanding, were valid <hi>ex poſt facto;</hi> but what he ſaith as to the Caſe of <hi>Polyga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> comes ſtill more home to our purpoſe, which though it was forbidden by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet a Divorce was not to enſue upon it; neither was the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Law leſs tender of a Divorce in the Caſe of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy</hi> with reſpect to ſuch Parties as had engaged in it, before they became Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Converts to Chriſtianity, than the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> was, though after our having once embrac'd that holy Profeſſion; it is now not only unlawful <hi>ex Antecedenti,</hi> but a Divorce ought to enſue at leaſt, beſides what other Puniſhments the Civil Laws ſhall think reaſonable to inflict after ſuch <hi>Polygamy</hi> is actually engaged in, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the general deſign of Chriſtianity, which aims much more earneſtly at all the higheſt inſtances of Charity and Good-will than the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſpenſation did: And therefore the ſtate of <hi>Polygamy,</hi> which is a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99229:6"/> natural occaſion of ſtrife, can never be a <hi>lawful Chriſtian</hi> State; but alſo becauſe this Union of the Husband to one Wife, as one and the ſame Fleſh is declar'd to be a <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol</hi> of the inſeparable Union of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his Church,</hi> and of the intire and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable Love of the one to the other: And on the other hand, <hi>Polygamy,</hi> by the Rule of Contraries, is a <hi>Symbol</hi> of <hi>Polythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm,</hi> or of the Worſhip of <hi>many</hi> and <hi>falſe</hi> Gods, which is the moſt directly oppoſite to Chriſtianity that any thing can poſſibly be conceiv'd to be: Wherefore, if the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and if the Chriſtian Diſpenſation it ſelf were ſo extremely tender of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce in this Caſe, notwithſtanding it was a plain diſobedience to an expreſs Divine Prohibition; how much more tender ought it to be in ours, where there is not only no Puniſhment aſſign'd (which we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be true of <hi>Polygamy</hi> it ſelf) but alſo no expreſs Prohibition to be found; and where the Breach of Charity, the Honour of Chriſtianity, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable reſpect and ſervice due to the True and Only God, are the two firſt of them not ſo much, and the latter not at all concern'd.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, It is very ſtrange, that there ſhould be ſo expreſs and careful a Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99229:7"/> of the Marriage of the <hi>Aunt</hi> with the <hi>Nephew</hi> as there is, <hi>Levit. 18. Verſ.</hi> 12, 13, 14. by which the <hi>Nephew</hi> is forbidden to Marry with his <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Mothers Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles Wife,</hi> which is all the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of <hi>Auntſhip</hi> that can be ſuppoſed: And that all theſe Caſes ſhould be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and ſo ſeverely puniſh'd as they are <hi>Levit. 20. verſ.</hi> 19, 20. and yet no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the leaſt made of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the <hi>Niece,</hi> whither of half or whole Blood, or whether by Conſanguity or Affinity in any wiſe whatſoever; ſo great ſollicitude on the one hand ſeems ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inconſiſtent with ſo great careleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſilence on the other, if the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> had intended to prohibit both theſe ſorts of Marriages alike.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, What Opinion our beſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers have had of Marriages of this kind, may be ſeen by theſe following Precedents, and Reports to be met with in their Books.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Pearſon</hi> in the time of King<note place="margin">Vaughan'<hi>s Reports,</hi> pag. 248.</note> 
               <hi>James the Firſt,</hi> Married his <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter,</hi> for which a Proceſs was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd againſt him in the Spiritual Court, and upon the Suit of the ſaid <hi>Richard Pearſon</hi> a Prohibition was granted out of the <hi>Common-Pleas;</hi> And it was reſolved by that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99229:7"/> Court, upon conſideration of the Statute 32 <hi>Hen. 8. Cap.</hi> 38. that the Marriage was not to be impeach'd, becauſe declar'd by the ſaid Act to be good, in as much as it was not prohibited by the <hi>Levitical</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and ſince <hi>Conſanguinities</hi> and <hi>Affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> as well by the <hi>Levitical</hi> as the <hi>Civil</hi> Law are the <hi>ſame,</hi> and prohibited to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degrees; it follows, that this Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age muſt be valid alſo, if this determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe <hi>Reverend Judges</hi> be good, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Conſanguinity at the ſame remove with the allow'd and ratify'd Affinity of this Inſtance. Much the ſame with this was the Caſe of <hi>Harriſon</hi> verſus <hi>Burwell: Harriſon</hi> had Married his <hi>great Aunt,</hi> the <hi>Widdow</hi> of <hi>Abbot</hi> his <hi>Grandfathers Brother,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi> declares this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to be valid, <hi>pag.</hi> 207. And not only ſo, but this Caſe by the Kings Command being referred to the Opinion of <hi>all</hi> the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd their Opinions, and accordingly Judgment was given, that a Prohibition ought to go to the Spiritual Court for the Plantiff.</p>
            <p>Now there is nothing more clear, than that the <hi>Aunt</hi> is expreſly forbidden to the <hi>Nephew</hi> in Marriage, and for this Reaſon, which the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> aſſigns, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99229:8"/> thine Aunt,</hi> thy <hi>Senior,</hi> thy <hi>Superior,</hi> and in Conſtruction of Law, <hi>Parentis loco,</hi> which holds as well, though not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and indeed the two firſt much more ſtrongly in the <hi>great Aunt,</hi> than in the <hi>Aunt</hi> at the <hi>firſt remove;</hi> but yet in the Judgment of theſe Learned Gentlemen, the Law of <hi>England</hi> proceeding only by the Letter without any regard, or at leaſt, very little to Parity of Reaſon, would not diſannul the Marriage of the <hi>great Aunt,</hi> though the <hi>immediate</hi> were ſo expreſly forbidden. Beſides this, my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi> gives it in general terms, as his Opinion, <hi>pag.</hi> 216. <q rend="margQuotes">The Marriages particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Acts to be againſt Gods Law, cannot be diſpenſed with; but other Marriages, not by the Acts declar'd in particular to be againſt Gods Law are left <hi>in Statu quo prius,</hi>
               </q> as to Diſpenſations with them, that is, ſo far as concerns the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees, they may be, and are actually diſpenſed with, as many as are not particularly and actually forbidden; not by the <hi>Pope,</hi> whoſe Power of Diſpenſation was now aboliſh'd and abrogated for ever; nor by any <hi>Prieſtly Abſolution,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts only for what is <hi>paſt,</hi> but cannot make any thing lawful <hi>de futuro,</hi> which either the Law of God or Man makes nul
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99229:8"/> and void; but by the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, which by not prohibiting ſuch Marriages hath made them lawful, which is exactly our Caſe, and therefore it muſt be lawful if my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi>'s Judgment be of any value. It is true indeed, in <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Good</hi>'s Caſe, he ſeems to vary one while from this determination, but within a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, he returns to his former mind, and confirms this Opinion by a fiction of a Caſe of a Man that had Married his <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter,</hi> before the third of <hi>November, 26 Hen.</hi> 8. by diſpenſation from <hi>Rome;</hi> and notwithſtanding, that all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations from <hi>Rome</hi> were afterwards made void, yet he declares this Marriage, being not prohibited by Gods Law, limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and declared in the Act of 28. <hi>Hen. 8. Cap.</hi> 7. to be by the expreſs words of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd Act, 28 <hi>H. 8. Cap.</hi> 16. a Marriage to continue good without ſeparation, as having a validity of its own to ſtand upon, extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to any thing of Diſpenſation from <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, When in the Act of 32 <hi>Hen. 8. Cap.</hi> 38. it is enacted, that, <hi>No Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Gods Law excepted, ſhall trouble or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach any Marriage without the</hi> Levitical <hi>Degrees.</hi> My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> declares it, as his Judgment, that if it had not been for thoſe words (<hi>Gods Law except</hi>) this Act had
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99229:9"/> excluded the Impeaching Marriages for <hi>plurality</hi> of <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Husbands</hi> at a time, for <hi>Impotency,</hi> and for <hi>Adultery,</hi> becauſe if the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees by our Law had been made the ſole and only meaſure of Prohibition, and if no Marriage could have been vacated but for offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe, our Law which keeps it ſelf ſtrictly to the Letter in theſe Caſes, would have taken no Cognizance of any ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment or obſtruction, as did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to one of theſe, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pretended in any of theſe three Caſes.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>Twentieth</hi> of <hi>Leviticus</hi> hath aſſign'd no Puniſhment, but that of preſent Death, in caſe of any inceſtuous or prohibited Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, as will appear to any Man that ſhall look over that Chapter. The Law knew no other Puniſhment for illegitimate Marriages, but Death; and therefore the Marriage which was not <hi>Capital</hi> was no offence at all againſt it, but was as Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate to all intents and purpoſes as any other Marriage in the World could be; and not only by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but by the <hi>Theodoſian Reſcript</hi> concerning <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> the next Degree to that which was <hi>Capital,</hi> was <hi>no</hi> Crime at all: For it do's not appear, that he forbad <hi>Second Couſins</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99229:9"/> to Marry. If then this Marriage of the Uncle to his Niece be ſo far from being expreſly puniſh'd by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that it is not any where ſo much as mention'd among the <hi>Levitical</hi> Reſtraints and Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions; if it be the hardeſt Caſe in Nature to put a Man and Woman to Death for a <hi>Conſequence,</hi> a <hi>real</hi> or <hi>pretended</hi> Parity of Reaſon, which either he, or ſhe, or both of them might very well not foreſee or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; and if, at laſt, there be <hi>no</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, <hi>no</hi> Parity in the Caſe, as will be undeniably manifeſted by and by; then it follows plainly, that the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to the <hi>Niece,</hi> is <hi>ſo far</hi> at leaſt Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, that it was not at all puniſhable by the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, and that it cannot be diſſolv'd by vertue of any Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament now extant among us, or by any other Power that will proceed either in Puniſhment or Prohibition upon the <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Meaſures.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, As there was no legal vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſeparation among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but by Death, unleſs, when an Husband for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his own had written a Bill of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce againſt his Wife; ſo the reaſon why Death was inflicted, ſeems to have been to prevent any Iſſue from ſuch Inceſtuous Conjunctions; or in the Language of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99229:10"/> Law it ſelf, that they might <hi>die Childleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Woman for endeavouring to bear, and the Man to beget at once a <hi>Spurious</hi> and Inceſtuous Off-ſpring. For a Baſtard, as it is every where a Name full of reproach, ſo among the <hi>Jews,</hi> he that was deſcended of an unlawful Bed, was look'd upon as an accurſed, abominable thing, and branded with peculiar and particular marks of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy and Deteſtation, and the Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents from him as far as to the <hi>Tenth Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> were not to <hi>enter into the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Lord, Deut.</hi> 23. 2. And this, though it ſhould happen, as it did for the moſt part, to be the effect of no more than <hi>Simple Fornication.</hi> And how much more deteſtable muſt ſuch a Baſtard needs be, who was the Off-ſpring of <hi>Inceſt</hi> and <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> (for ſuch ſort of Marriages were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed no better) in a moſt execrable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction and Combination together.</p>
            <p>But now it is certainly a very hard Caſe to make any Man a <hi>Baſtard</hi> by <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, becauſe his Father and Mother happened to do ſome thing which it was impoſſible for him to hinder, which is like another thing which is forbidden, much leſs is there any Baſtardy in ſuch a Caſe, where the Parity of Reaſon do's not hold; and whereever the Off-ſpring is not <hi>Spuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99229:10"/> the Marriage is <hi>Legitimate:</hi> For a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate</hi> Son or Daughter cannot poſſibly be deſcended but of <hi>Legitimate</hi> Parents. And the better to remove all obſtacles as to this matter, out of the way, it is to be obſerv'd, that, as to the Phraſe of <hi>Dying Childleſs,</hi> the Interpretation juſt now given, is confirm'd by the Authority of the Learned Jeſuite <hi>Stephanus Menochius,</hi> who in his Comment upon that place hath theſe remarkable words to the very ſame Senſe with mine, <hi>Hi inceſtuoſi non ſinentur in hoc ſcelere permanere donec liberos babere poſſint, ſed occidantur;</hi> and this, when all is done, is the true meaning of the Text; though the <hi>Jews,</hi> who are horribly unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the remote Antiquities of their own Nation, have deviſed other <hi>fanciful</hi> Gloſſes which will not abide the teſt of a <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Enquiry: And that we may not wonder at this ſeverity of puniſhing all Inceſtuous Conjunctions with Death, <hi>Paulutius Foroju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienſis</hi> refers it, as he very well might, beſides the Reaſon given, to the Arbitrary diſpoſal of Almighty God, who may annex what Sanction he pleaſes to his Laws; or, which is all one, to ſome Impulſive Cauſe or Motive which he hath not thought fit to reveal, ſo that with reſpect to us it is Arbitrary, let it be what it will in it ſelf; where
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99229:11"/> ſpeaking of <hi>Congreſs</hi> with a <hi>Menſtruous</hi> Woman being puniſh'd with Death, he ſays, <hi>Multa alia quae non ſunt peccata Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia puniebantur poenâ mortis ex aliquâ cauſa legiſlatorem movente, ut eſus Sanguinis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, It is certain, that <hi>Amram</hi> took to Wife <hi>Jochebed</hi> his <hi>Fathers Siſter;</hi> and this could not be long before the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Law, for of that Match <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> were deſcended. The thing is mention'd in more places than one of the Scripture, without any manner of blame or reprehenſion; and we are not raſhly to ſuppoſe Perſons that were ſo highly honour'd by God with a <hi>Prophetick</hi> Spirit, a Gift of <hi>Miracles,</hi> a <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter annex'd for ever to the Family of the one, and a <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power inveſted by God himſelf in the Perſon of the other, to have been <hi>ſpurious</hi> or <hi>illegitimate:</hi> From whence it follows, that whatever Reaſons of Convenience or Intereſt there may be to hinder ſuch Marriages from being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into, yet it was not a Matter of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and indiſpenſible Obligation, till after the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes;</hi> and that if it had not been for the giving of that Law, it would have remain'd ſtill in the ſame prudential indifference which it had before; for what is once Lawful, muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99229:11"/> continue ſo, till a <hi>ſupervening</hi> Law forbids it, and makes it unlawful. But if the Marriage of the <hi>Nephew</hi> to his <hi>Aunt</hi> were a Marriage <hi>good</hi> and <hi>valid</hi> before the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to his <hi>Niece</hi> was much more, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in many repects a more favourable Caſe, as ſhall be hereafter declar'd; and therefore not being any where expreſly forbidden, it muſt continue ſtill as it was, Prudential and Indifferent, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lawful: For when Reſtraints are laid upon lawful things, there is no Inference from the Prohibition of one thing to the Prohibition of another, by <hi>parity</hi> of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whether <hi>pretended</hi> or <hi>real;</hi> but the Prohibition ſtops within it ſelf, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no further than the Letter: As if part of a Common Field ſhould be enclos'd, and this Encloſure eſtabliſh'd and warranted by Law; there lies here no Inference by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Reaſon for the Encloſure of the reſt, but what is not actually and legally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd, is Common, and muſt remain open, as it did before.</p>
            <p>Beſides, That <hi>Moſes,</hi> by God's appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould ſo ſeverely forbid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> a ſort of Marriage of which he himſelf and his Brother <hi>Aaron</hi> were deſcended, bringing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99229:12"/> by that means a ſort of Aſperſion, and ſomething that is, at leaſt, very like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, upon himſelf and his Family, upon his Brother <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Family of <hi>Prieſts</hi> that were for ever after deſcended from his Loins, and yet take no notice in the leaſt of the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> in which he was not concern'd, but might have forbidden it without any manner of Reflexion upon himſelf or his Relations, if God had intended to prohibit them both alike, is a thing to me ſo incredible, that nothing can be more; and, I preſume, it will appear ſo to every indifferent Perſon that ſhall reflect upon it.</p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, There is alſo the Caſe of <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel,</hi> in the Books of <hi>Joſuah</hi> and <hi>Judges;</hi> in which if we underſtand the Text ſo as that <hi>Othniel,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Half-brother</hi> of <hi>Caleb</hi> by the <hi>Mohters Side,</hi> for <hi>Caleb</hi> was not the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> but <hi>Jephunneh</hi>) then here is another Inſtance, after the Law, of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> marrying his <hi>Niece,</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Half-Brother by the Mothers Side. The words of the Text are theſe, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 15. 17. Othniel <hi>the Son of</hi> Kenaz, <hi>the Brother of</hi> Caleb, <hi>took it</hi> (Kirjath-ſepher) <hi>and he gave him</hi> Achſah <hi>his Daughter to Wiſe.</hi> And again, <hi>Judges</hi> 1. 13. Othniel
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99229:12"/> 
               <hi>the Son of</hi> Kenaz, Caleb's <hi>younger Brother, took it</hi> (Kirjath-ſepher): Which words in both places may either be ſo interpreted, that <hi>Othniel</hi> had this double Relation, he was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> and he was likewiſe <hi>Caleb's</hi> younger Brother by the Mothers Side; and then <hi>Achſah</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Caleb</hi> will be <hi>Othniel</hi>'s Niece, and his <hi>Niece</hi> by a nearer Conſanguinity than that in the Caſe before us: Or elſe, that <hi>Othniel</hi> was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> which <hi>Kenaz</hi> was younger Brother to <hi>Caleb;</hi> and ſo <hi>Othniel</hi> and <hi>Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſah</hi> will be <hi>Couſin-Germans.</hi> Both of theſe Interpretations, if there were nothing elſe but theſe words to be conſider'd, are very natural and eaſie; but when we conſider, that after the Death of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſuah</hi> the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were made Captive by <hi>Cuſhan-riſhathaim</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>Eight years,</hi> Judg. 3. 8. that God rais'd up this <hi>Othniel</hi> to be their <hi>Saviour</hi> and Deliverer out of the Hands of their Oppreſſor, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. and that the <hi>Land had reſt</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under the Government of this <hi>Othniel</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>Forty years;</hi> no Man will ever think, that <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> in that Age of the World could probably be the Sons of the ſame Mother, when it is ſo plainly demonſtrable, that there was at leaſt <hi>Forty nine</hi> or <hi>Fifty</hi> years difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99229:13"/> their Ages; for to this <hi>Forty eight</hi> we muſt add <hi>One</hi> or <hi>Two</hi> more, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Period began they were both <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary,</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> if he were Brother to <hi>Othniel,</hi> was then the Elder by a Year or two at the leaſt.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 8. we have an Account that <hi>Joſuah</hi> died, and <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that <hi>all that Generation,</hi> of which <hi>Caleb</hi> was one, <hi>were gather'd to their Fathers;</hi> and then before this Revolution of <hi>Cuſhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhathaim,</hi> we have an account of ſeveral other Oppreſſions which the <hi>Jews</hi> for their many Sins and Provocations labour'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. So that the diſtance between the Age of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> is ſtill conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly greater than what hath been repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It remains therefore, that <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> were <hi>Couſin-germans,</hi> that is, <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Children,</hi> who in their Circumſtance might lawfully marry; for it appears, that <hi>Achſah</hi> was an <hi>Heireſs,</hi> otherwiſe her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could not have given her the <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as he did, and added afterwards to it <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper and the Nether Springs;</hi> all which, by the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Platform of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, would otherwiſe have devolv'd upon the <hi>Male Iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask, how any Woman can be call'd an <hi>Heireſs,</hi> while her Father is yet
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99229:13"/> living; I anſwer, That in ſtrictneſs ſhe could not yet be call'd by that Name, there being no Inheritance neceſſarily devolv'd upon her; but her Father was now ſo old, that he was paſt the hope or expectation of any more Children: For at the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the Wilderneſs, he was one of the <hi>Heads of the Tribes, Numb.</hi> 13. 6. and one of thoſe who together with <hi>Joſuah</hi> and others, <hi>v.</hi> 17. were ſent by <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>ſpy out the Land of Canaan.</hi> After this they remain'd in the Wilderneſs <hi>Forty years;</hi> and <hi>Joſuah,</hi> who ſeems to have been much of the ſame Age with <hi>Caleb,</hi> ſoon after his entrance upon the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> died, being at his death of the Age of <hi>an hundred and ten</hi> years, <hi>Joſ. 24. 29. Judg.</hi> 2. 8. And if we allow <hi>Ten</hi> or <hi>Twenty</hi> years, by which <hi>Joſuah,</hi> without any Reaſon that appears, ſhall be ſuppos'd to be older than <hi>Caleb,</hi> the Age of <hi>Caleb</hi> at the Marriage of his Daughter <hi>Achſah</hi> will be an <hi>Hundred,</hi> or <hi>Ninety</hi> at leaſt: Wherefore being ſo old, and unfit in Perſon to be at the Head of a vigorous Aſſault, he propounds the taking of <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jath-ſepher</hi> to ſome other, with a Reward: <hi>He that ſmiteth</hi> Kirjath-ſepher, <hi>and taketh it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to him will I give</hi> Achſah <hi>my Daughter to Wife.</hi> Not that any <hi>One</hi> Man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99229:14"/> could take a <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Town</hi> by <hi>himſelf,</hi> or that <hi>every</hi> Man was fit to command a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or that the Inheritance which was to go along with <hi>Achſah</hi> could be legally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from <hi>Othniel,</hi> who was the next <hi>Heir-male</hi> of that Family; only by theſe general Words he propounds the Conduct of the Expedition to <hi>Othniel,</hi> with promiſe upon Succeſs that he ſhould be immediately married to his Daughter, which the Old Man during his Life-time was not oblig'd to permit, and have part of the Inheritance before-hand. And this is the true State of this Caſe; which tho' in it ſelf it be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to our purpoſe, yet there is an uſe that may be made of it, and that is this.</p>
            <p>That it would be very ſtrange, if God had intended equally to prohibit the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> with that of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> not only that he ſhould no where expreſly prohibit the <hi>former</hi> of theſe, as he hath done the <hi>latter;</hi> but that the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> in this particular Caſe of <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel,</hi> ſhould ſpeak of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin-Germans</hi> after ſuch a manner, that many, and thoſe very Learned Men too, have been induc'd to believe, it was the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece;</hi> for of this Opinion were moſt of thoſe, whom I have already cited,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99229:14"/> as Aſſertors of the meerly poſitive Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law.</p>
            <p>Fifteenthly, As to the Pretence of Parity of Reaſon by which a <hi>Niece</hi> and her <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> are debarr'd from Marriage, becauſe the <hi>Aunt</hi> and her <hi>Nephew</hi> are expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, there are theſe following things to be ſaid in anſwer to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>Rabbinical</hi> or <hi>Talmudical</hi> Jews did allow of the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> with his <hi>Niece;</hi> which tho' the <hi>Karrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> or <hi>Scripturary Jews</hi> did not, yet this is ſo far from doing any prejudice to this Cauſe, that, on the contrary, it is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt advantage to it; becauſe this is a plain Sign, that the <hi>Talmudiſts,</hi> who could not be ignorant of this diſagreement of the <hi>Karraitiſh</hi> Faction, did not err through Inadvertency, as too frequently they do; but their Opinion was partly founded upon the Tradition of their Church, and partly upon one of theſe two Reaſons, either that Parity of Reaſon was not to be admitted in any of theſe <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Affairs, or that indeed there was no ſuch Parity as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as will be ſhewn immediately that there is not. And tho' the Traditions of the <hi>Jewiſh Maſters</hi> are in many Caſes very uncertain, and in others plainly falſe; yet where Tradition and Reaſon do conſpire
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99229:15"/> together, they give a mutual Strength and Reputation to each other.</p>
            <p>For, in the ſecond place, it is plain, that this Parity will not hold, and that upon theſe ſeveral accounts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the Marriage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> the natural Subordination of Relations is deſtroy'd, and the true Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Things upon one another. A <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior,</hi> as the <hi>Aunt</hi> unqueſtionably was, and one that was <hi>loco Parentis,</hi> as well by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> as the <hi>Civil</hi> Law, as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> hath prov'd in his <hi>Reſolutiou of Three Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Caſes,</hi> was forc'd to ſubmit not only to all the <hi>Familiarities</hi> of a <hi>Wife,</hi> but alſo to all the <hi>Slaveries</hi> of a <hi>Servant;</hi> for <hi>Wives</hi> were no better according to the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Whereas in the other Caſe, of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> marrying with his <hi>Niece,</hi> the natural Dependence was preſerv'd, ſhe being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready his <hi>Inferior</hi> and his <hi>Servant.</hi> The Impiety of this ſort of Marriage of a Man to his <hi>Superior,</hi> and to her that in Legal Conſtruction was <hi>Parentis loco,</hi> is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by <hi>Papinius Statius:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—illum illum ſacris adhibete Nefaſtis,</l>
               <l>Qui laeto dedit enſe patrem, qui ſemet in ortus</l>
               <l>Vertit &amp; indignae regerit ſua pignora Matri.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99229:15"/>
            <p>And by <hi>Lucan,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Cui fas implere Parentem,</l>
               <l>Quid rear eſſe Nefas—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which Places tho' they be indeed meant of the Mother in the moſt <hi>proper</hi> ſenſe, yet they may be extended without immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſtraining to all that are <hi>Parentum loco.</hi> And to this purpoſe the manner of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is remarkable, <hi>Lev. 18. 14. Thou ſhalt not uncover the nakedneſs of thy Fathers Brother; thou ſhalt not approach to his Wife: ſhe is thine Aunt:</hi> as much as to ſay, that though ſhe be of kin to thee only by <hi>affinity,</hi> being only thy <hi>Fathers Brothers Wife,</hi> and coming from <hi>abroad</hi> out of a <hi>Foreign</hi> Stock, yet ſhe is <hi>thine Aunt,</hi> ſhe is <hi>Parentis loco</hi> notwithſtanding: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a great Irreverence, and a very high and heinous Breach of Duty and Good Manners in thee, to <hi>uncover her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs.</hi> And <hi>Phaedra</hi> in <hi>Seneca</hi> being deeply enamourd of her Son-in-Law <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polytus,</hi> and yet knowing the Diſgrace and Infamy of a <hi>Mother-in-Law</hi> lying down to her <hi>Son,</hi> tho' this were only a Relation of <hi>Affinity,</hi> and not really ſo near a kin as the <hi>Aunt</hi> by the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mothers</hi> Side, was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99229:16"/> deſirous to forget that Name for good and all: For thus ſhe ſays;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Matris ſuperbum eſt nomen &amp; nimium potens,</l>
               <l>Noſtros humilius nomen affectus decet,</l>
               <l>Me vel Sororem, <hi>Hippolyte,</hi> vel famulam voca.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Secondly, In the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to the <hi>Niece</hi> there is greater fitneſs for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation, which is the great and declar'd end of Marriage, than in that of the <hi>Aunt</hi> to the <hi>Nephew.</hi> And this Argument is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the leſs cogent, becauſe <hi>Albericus Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilis</hi> knew three or four <hi>Bonny, Brisk Aunts,</hi> that were younger than their <hi>Nephews,</hi> and his own Aunt, it ſeems, was one of the number: For a Law is a general Rule, which regards only the generality of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, without regard to thoſe that are ſo rare, and ſo ſeldom to be met with; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that there are other Reaſons upon which the Marriage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew</hi> is prohibited; and where this do's not hold, the others do. It is enough, that generally ſpeaking, <hi>Aunts</hi> are much Older than their <hi>Nephews,</hi> and that Women do not continue fit for Generation ſo long as Men, by which means it comes to paſs, tho' the <hi>Aunt</hi> at the time of Marriage may not in many Inſtances be <hi>effaete</hi> and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99229:16"/> yet ſhe will not continue <hi>Prolifick</hi> ſo long as a <hi>Niece:</hi> So that there is a double natural Obſtruction againſt the Marriage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> which do's not hold in that of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, If we conſider the ſame Man as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with reſpect to his <hi>Niece,</hi> and as a <hi>Nephew</hi> with reſpect to his <hi>Aunt,</hi> here are <hi>three</hi> Terms at a diſtance from each other, and the <hi>two Extremes</hi> are probably very far aſunder: There is, in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Youth, Beauty, and Virginity, on the one hand; and on the other, Old Age, Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhood, and an <hi>imparturient</hi> Eſtate. So that, <hi>generally ſpeaking,</hi> there is manifeſtly a greater Temptation to the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with the <hi>Niece,</hi> than to that of the <hi>Nephew</hi> with his <hi>Aunt;</hi> therefore if the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> had intended to forbid the <hi>former,</hi> as well as the <hi>latter,</hi> this is that which ought to have been prohibited in the firſt place, becauſe there is the greater Temptation to it; and therefore the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Tranſgreſſion muſt of neceſſity be more frequent. Neither can any thing be a greater diſparagement to the Wiſdom of God, than to ſay, that he intended both of theſe ſorts of Marriages ſhould be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void; and yet at the ſame time to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate that with ſo much ſeeming induſtry
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99229:17"/> and ſolicitude, of which there was ſcarce any danger; and to omit that wholly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt word of notice, whoſe Danger was ſo apparent, whoſe Temptation is ſo ſtrong, and whoſe Inſtances, without a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſevere and peremptory Prohibition, could not, in all probability, be unfrequent.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, When it is ſaid, <hi>Levit. 18. 6. None of you ſhall approach to any that is near of kin to him to uncover their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> it is to be obſerv'd, that this <hi>Nearneſs of Kin</hi> is to be meaſur'd not from <hi>our ſelves,</hi> but from the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Kindred, that is, from a <hi>Common Father</hi> or <hi>Parent;</hi> as when it is ſaid in the Prohibition of the <hi>Aunt by the Father's Side,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>Thou ſhalt not uncover the Nakedneſs of thy Father's Siſter, ſhe is thy Father's near Kinſwoman:</hi> And again, ver. 13. <hi>of the Aunt by the Mothers Side, Thou ſhalt not uncover the Nakedneſs of thy Mothers Siſter, for ſhe is thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers near Kinſwoman:</hi> It is plain, that tho' my <hi>Niece</hi> be at the ſame diſtance from me in the deſcending Line, that mine <hi>Aunt</hi> is in the aſcending; yet when the expreſs Reaſon aſſign'd in the Law, why I may not marry mine <hi>Aunt,</hi> is not becauſe ſhe is <hi>mine,</hi> but my <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Mothers</hi> near Kinſwoman, this is ſo far from darting any Prohibition upon my <hi>Niece,</hi> that it is, on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99229:17"/> the contrary, plainly favourable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to a Marriage in that Relation; becauſe my <hi>Niece,</hi> who is my <hi>Father's Grandchild,</hi> is plainly at a further diſtance from him, than <hi>mine Aunt,</hi> who is his <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> and that for two Reaſons. Firſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the one is an <hi>Immediate</hi> Relation; but the other, by the <hi>Interpoſition</hi> of a Son or Daughter betwixt, is a Relation at the <hi>Second remove:</hi> And becauſe <hi>no</hi> Man or Woman can get or bear Children by <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> without the Conjunction of <hi>another,</hi> it is therefore only a Relation by the <hi>Half Blood;</hi> and if it be the <hi>Niece</hi> by the <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> there is not only the <hi>Half Blood</hi> to be conſider'd, but that <hi>that</hi> Half Blood <hi>it ſelf</hi> is the more <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity of the two, as will be ſeen hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. So that if the <hi>Nearneſs</hi> to my <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> be the <hi>expreſs</hi> Reaſon aſſign'd in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> why I may not marry mine <hi>Aunt,</hi> no Man can with any ſhew of Reaſon infer from thence, that I am forbid likewiſe to marry my <hi>Niece,</hi> becauſe the Diſtance is manifeſtly <hi>greater</hi> from the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Kindred, and the Relation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably more <hi>imperfect.</hi> So alſo, when it is ſaid, <hi>ver. 14. Thou ſhalt not uncover the Nakedneſs of thy Father's Brother, thou ſhalt not approach to his Wife, ſhe is thine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99229:18"/> Aunt,</hi> here there are three things manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imply'd.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That in the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prohibitions <hi>Conſangninities</hi> and <hi>Affinities</hi> are conſider'd as the <hi>ſame,</hi> and are prohibited to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degrees. Secondly, That the Reaſon of her being forbidden in Marriage, is becauſe ſhe is my <hi>Fathers Brothers Wife;</hi> that is, in conſtruction of Law, my <hi>Fathers Siſter</hi> or <hi>near Kinſwoman.</hi> And thirdly, as in the two former Caſes, That this is done out of Reſpect and Honour to my Father, with whom ſhe ſtands upon the <hi>ſame Level</hi> or <hi>Horizontal</hi> Plane in the <hi>Scheme</hi> of <hi>Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity,</hi> or <hi>Affinity;</hi> ſo that to marry mine <hi>Aunt,</hi> is to make my <hi>Father's Equal</hi> my <hi>Inferior,</hi> and to ſubject her to the <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>ſervile</hi> Condition of a <hi>Wife,</hi> to whom I own the <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of a <hi>Parent.</hi> And this is the true Interpretation of thoſe words in this laſt place, <hi>She is thine Aunt;</hi> for every Man knows, without the help of <hi>Revelation,</hi> that his <hi>Fathers Brothers Wife</hi> is his <hi>Aunt;</hi> but there is manifeſtly inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in them an intimation of her <hi>Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> over us, by reaſon of her ſtanding equal in the Table of <hi>Affinity</hi> with our <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother;</hi> and therefore ſhe ought not to ſubmit to have her Nakedneſs uncover'd by her <hi>Inferior</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pendent,</hi> or put her ſelf
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99229:18"/> into a Condition of <hi>Subjection</hi> to him, from whom ſhe may expect and challenge the Duty, Service, and Allegiance of a <hi>Son.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Greeks</hi> call'd the Uncle and Aunt by the Names of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, alluding, as I ſuppoſe, in the uſe of theſe words, to the Ancient, Abſolute, and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, which all Parents had over their Children; ſo that as to all the Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to which their Power or poſſibility of Action could extend it ſelf, they were as abſolute and unaccountable as <hi>God himſelf,</hi> and were his <hi>Vicegerents</hi> upon Earth in their reſpective Families; and the Uncle and Aunt were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, they has as it were <hi>aliquid divini juris in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros liberaſque fratrum &amp; ſororum,</hi> they had a Right of Reverence, and a natural Claim of Duty and Reſpect from their <hi>Nephews</hi> and <hi>Nieces,</hi> which were accounted but a Remove from <hi>Children,</hi> and laid ſo great a weight upon all their Advices, Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Commands, that to diſobey them in any thing not very unreaſonable, was accounted an heinous Crime, altho' their Power of Coercion were not all out ſo great as that of their natural and proper Parents.</p>
            <p>And now from what hath been juſt now ſaid it is plain, that the Reaſon of that Law
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99229:19"/> by which the <hi>Nephew</hi> is prohibited to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his <hi>Aunt,</hi> being founded in theſe two things; Firſt, in <hi>Nearneſs of Kin,</hi> which is greater to the <hi>Father</hi> in his <hi>Siſter</hi> than in his <hi>Grandchild:</hi> Secondly, in the <hi>Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and <hi>Preeminence</hi> of the <hi>Aunt</hi> over the <hi>Nephew;</hi> I ſay, it is plain, that it cannot from either of theſe Conſiderations be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd by any Parity of Reaſon, that the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece</hi> is forbidden; and with reſpect to the latter Conſideration, the <hi>Superiority</hi> is not viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſuch a Marriage, but rather pleas'd and gratified by it, becauſe it ſtill continues where it was, that is, in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle;</hi> only by Marriage it is rendred more abſolute and perfect: So that unleſs Contraries may by Parity of Reaſon be inferr'd from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, there can be no Inference from the Prohibition of an <hi>Aunt,</hi> which ſhall debar or obſtruct the Marriage of a <hi>Niece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it being ſo clear as it is, that there is no Parity of Reaſon between the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> and that of a <hi>Nephew</hi> with his <hi>Aunt,</hi> it is now manifeſt, if we proceed upon the <hi>Levitical</hi> Meaſures, that the Divorce of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> from his <hi>Niece</hi> is not only indefeſible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are once married, but that, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the <hi>Levitical</hi> as a Poſitive Law, it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99229:19"/> is lawful <hi>ex antecedenti,</hi> ſince it is neither forbidden in <hi>expreſs</hi> words, neither can it be inferr'd to be unlawful by <hi>parity</hi> of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and ſince the Meaſures of the <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Law are in this Caſe of Matrimony the declar'd Meaſures of ours, it follows una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably, that what is left indifferent in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> preſerves the ſame Liberty and Indifference in ours.</p>
            <p>In the ſixteenth place, it is ſtill further to be conſider'd, That Cohabitation it ſelf, if it have been of long continuance, is in Law a powerful Remedy againſt other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; for ſo we have it upon the Authority of <hi>Servius, Tribus modis apud veteres nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fiebant,</hi> (uſu Farre &amp; Coemptione) <hi>uſu ſi verbi gratia Mulier anno uno cum viro li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet ſine legibus fuiſſet, &amp;c.</hi> So that if the Parties married together, and ſtanding in this Relation, have cohabited for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, this is one great Argument, and hath been all along ſo taken in the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> Law againſt a Divorce, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there be a Fault admitted in their firſt coming together.</p>
            <p>Seventeenthly, This Caſe being only the <hi>Niece</hi> by the <hi>Half Blood</hi> on the <hi>Fathers Side,</hi> which is the more weak and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, this is ſtill a farther Circumſtance ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much conducing to favour, and defends it,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99229:20"/> as appears by the Caſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who married his <hi>Half Siſter</hi> by the <hi>Fathers Side:</hi> For had ſhe been his <hi>Whole Siſter,</hi> ſhe could not have been his <hi>Wife.</hi> And this is that which he urges in his own Defence to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> the King of <hi>Gerar, She is the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my Father, but not the Daughter of my Mother; and ſhe became my Wife.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 6. it is provided in Caſe of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, If thy Brother, the Son of thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or thy Son, or thy Daughter, or the Wife of thy Boſom, or thy Friend which is as thine own Soul, entice thee ſecretly, ſaying, Let us go and ſerve other Gods, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 8. <hi>Thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hearken unto him, neither ſhall thine Eye pity him, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, neither ſhalt thou conceal him:</hi> ver. 9. <hi>But thou ſhalt ſurely kill him: thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meaning of which Law is, That <hi>Idolatry</hi> ſhould certainly be puniſh'd with <hi>Death,</hi> let the Relation be never ſo <hi>nigh,</hi> or the Endearment and Friendſhip never ſo <hi>great,</hi> as appears by thoſe words, <hi>or the Wife of thy Boſom, or thy Friend which is as thine own Soul:</hi> And when it is ſaid, <hi>Thy Brother the Son of thy Mother,</hi> without mention of the <hi>Brother by the Father,</hi> it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99229:20"/> is imply'd, that the one is <hi>nearer</hi> of Kin than the other in the Interpretation of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law; this beſt anſwering the Intention of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which did oblige them not to conceal even their <hi>near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> Relations: And in this Prohibition the Brother being the <hi>Son</hi> or <hi>ſuppos'd Son of the Father,</hi> is included <hi>à fortiori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The whole ſtreſs of our <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> Cauſe is grounded upon <hi>Archbiſhop Parker</hi>'s Matrimonial Table; and tho' we are far from preſuming to diſpute the King's Power in diſpenſing with a Statute in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Neceſſity, of which He is the Judge; yet in all Ordinary Caſes He is never ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to intend it: And it is certain, that when, among other Articles preſented to Him by the Convocation, he gave the <hi>Royal</hi> Aſſent to the <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Table, in which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> is prohibited to marry his <hi>Niece,</hi> the Convocation themſelves were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that this Degree was ſome way or other prohibited by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and the King agreed to this Prohibition, among others, upon that Suppoſition: But now, ſince it appears ſo plainly, that this ſort of Marriage was never <hi>actually</hi> forbidden by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor ſo much as <hi>intended</hi> to be forbidden; either nothing but God's Law can impeach any Marriage, and by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99229:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſequence this cannot be impeach'd; or elſe an Act of Parliament may be repeal'd by an Act of Convocation, which yet hath no power to make any Laws or Ordinances whatſoever; but what the Parliament it ſelf hath given it; and the Parliament can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſuppos'd to put a Power deſtructive of their very Conſtitution, into the Hands of the Clergy met together in a Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: nay, they have expreſly provided, with the King's Royal Aſſent, who without Neceſſity, which cannot here be pretended, will never break his Word with his People, (and then the Breach of it is the trueſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) that no Convocation ſhall exerciſe any ſuch Power.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99229:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
